<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ubuntu | Daves dev warblings]]></title>
  <link href="http://jedistirfry.co.uk/blog/categories/ubuntu/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jedistirfry.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-14T15:27:10+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jedistirfry.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Yell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sharing folders from a Mac to Ubuntu using Samba]]></title>
    <link href="http://jedistirfry.co.uk/blog/2013-01/loading-remote-shares/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-18T09:43:25+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jedistirfry.co.uk/blog/2013-01/loading-remote-shares</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So due to snow I had to work from home. I needed to mount my work files over the VPN so that I could use my work Mac as my server. This would save me loads of time, allowing me to edit the files remotely and view them using my Macs nginx server.</p>

<h2>Using Samba / CIFS</h2>

<h3>Setup</h3>

<p>For this method you&rsquo;ll need to enable file sharing on the Mac locally in <strong>System Preferences</strong> > <strong>Sharing</strong> and enable <strong>File Sharing</strong>. Then you&rsquo;ll want to share a folder, probably your home folder, <code>/Users/david</code>. Hit <strong>Options</strong> and enable sharing with SMB. Be sure to click the account that you want to use, and enter your password.</p>

<h3>Connecting to the share</h3>

<p>In Ubuntu or Windows, you should be able to connect to the folder using the IP address of your computer, in the format of <code>smb://192.168.0.1</code> then enter your local machine login.</p>

<h3>Mounting the share</h3>

<p>Check to make sure that you have <code>cifs</code> installed by looking for <code>cifs-utils</code> package.<br/>
<code>bash
dpkg --get-selections cifs-utils
</code><br/>
If not, you&rsquo;ll need to install it. <code>sudo apt-get install cifs-utils</code>.</p>

<p>In terminal<br/>
<code>bash
sudo mount -t cifs //server/share -o 'username=david,password=mypassword,rw,nounix,noserverinfo,sec=ntlmssp,file_mode=0777,dir_mode=0777' /mnt/david_mac
</code></p>

<h2>Using NFS</h2>

<h3>Setup</h3>

<p>Firstly you need to edit the <code>/etc/exports</code> on the Mac to add the folder that you want to share. Something like <code>"/Users/david" -alldirs -mapall=501</code> will share the home folder to everyone on your network, fine for internal mounting.</p>

<p>Next we need to make sure that the file is correct and nfsd is running.</p>

<pre><code class="bash">$ showmount -e
$ sudo nfsd checkexports
$ sudo nfsd status
$ sudo nfsd restart
$ showmount -e
</code></pre>

<h3>Mount the share</h3>

<p><code>sudo mount -t nfs -o 'proto=tcp,port=2049,nolock' hostname:/Users/david /mnt/david_mac/</code></p>

<h2>Done</h2>

<p>Have a celebratory cup of tea. You deserve it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Allow alt-tab across all viewports in Ubuntu]]></title>
    <link href="http://jedistirfry.co.uk/blog/2013-01/unity-alt-tab/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-16T09:43:25+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jedistirfry.co.uk/blog/2013-01/unity-alt-tab</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I dev at work on a Mac and at home in an Ubuntu VM. On my Ubuntu machine I tend to spread my apps across multiple viewports for ease of organisation. However the new Ubuntu Unity plugin for Compiz means that alt-tab only works for your current viewport. Not ideal.</p>

<h3>First thing&rsquo;s first</h3>

<p>You&rsquo;ll need to install the CompizConfig Settings Manager. You can find this in the software centre by searching for &lsquo;<strong>Compiz</strong>&rsquo;, or you can install it from Terminal using <code>sudo apt-get install compizconfig-settings-manager</code>.</p>

<h3>Configure Unity</h3>

<p>Once this is installed it should appear in your applications bar on the left. If not, hit the Ubuntu button and type &lsquo;Compiz&rsquo;.</p>

<p>Scroll down to the third section, and click on the &lsquo;<strong>Ubuntu Unity Plugin</strong>&rsquo;. Click on the &lsquo;<strong>Switcher</strong>&rsquo; tab at the top, and then untick the &lsquo;<strong>Bias alt-tab to prefer windows on the current viewport</strong>&rsquo;.</p>

<h3>Make a brew!</h3>

<p>That&rsquo;s it. Job done. Happy alt-tabbing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
